Finding Aid for Reuben Leon Kahn Papers 1915-1979
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Reuben Leon Kahn Papers 1915-1979
Kahn, Reuben Leon
The Reuben Leon Kahn collection consists of the personal and professional papers of the developer of the Kahn precipitation test for syphilis. Kahn taught bacteriology and serology at the University of Michigan from 1928 until his retirement in 1956.
851598 Aa 2
5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The bulk of the collection was donated by Kahn's estate (Donor No. 5083 ) in 1979.
The collection is open for research.
Dr. Reuben L. Kahn, professor of bacteriology and serology at the University of Michigan from 1928 to 1956, is best known for developing the Kahn precipitation test for syphilis. However, Kahn, who remained an active researcher until the age of 85, also carried out extensive research in the areas of tissue immunity and cancer irradiation. In addition to his contributions to the medical profession, Kahn was actively concerned with civil rights and human understanding.
Reuben Kahn was born in Lithuania in 1887 and immigrated to America with his family at age 12. He first became interested in medical research as an undergraduate at Valparaiso University. After graduating from here in 1909 he obtained an M.S. from Yale in 1913 and a D.Sc. from New York University in 1916. From 1917 to 1919 Kahn served in the Army Sanitary Corp.
In 1923, while working as an immunologist for the Michigan State Department of Health, Kahn developed the precipitation test for syphilis, which came to be known as the Kahn test. He was appointed director of laboratories of the University Hospitals at the University of Michigan in 1928, where he also became professor of bacteriology and, in 1957, professor of serology. During the 1930's Kahn began his work on tissue immunity, studying the capacity of tissue to localize foreign substances. In 1956, at the age of 69, he became involved in research on the subject of irradiation and tissue localization. This research continued into the 1970's, funded by the Atomic Energy Commission from 1957 to 1967, the American Cancer Society from 1967 to 1969, and the National Cancer Institute from 1969 to 1973. Although Kahn retired from the University of Michigan faculty in 1956, he ,continued to carry out his research at Michigan until 1968 when he became professor of microbiology at Howard University, retiring in 1973.
Kahn and his wife, Dina, were active in the National Conference of Christians and Jews. Kahn's concern with racial equality was demonstrated as early as 1928, when he hired the first black to work in the University Medical Center laboratories. Kahn died in 1979.
The Kahn papers are likely to prove of most interest to biographers and to researchers interested in Kahn's experiments and his approach to research. The correspondence series provides insight into both Kahn's family life and his professional development. Speeches and papers in the collection give an indication of his personal philosophy. Materials relating to his research mostly concern his later studies on tissue immunity and irradiation. The Kahn papers are also significant as an indication of the potential contribution of older people to society.
The Reuben L. Kahn papers contain materials relevant to Kahn's personal and professional life. The collection is divided into five series; Biographical Materials, Correspondence, Topical Files, Publications and Photographs.
Subjects:
Kahn, Reuben L. (Reuben Leon), 1887-1979.; Physicians--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Scientists--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Syphilis.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Medical School.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Kahn, Reuben L. (Reuben Leon), 1887-1979.; Kahn family.; Laboratories.; Physicians--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Medical School.; Classrooms--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Biographical Materials
  The Biographical Materials series contains both autobiographical and biographical material on Kahn's career and life.
  - Autobiographical material (Box 1)
  - Biographical material (Box 1)
- Correspondence 1915-1977
  The Correspondence series is organized by and contains materials of both a personal and professional nature. The dates range from 1915 to 1977, with the bulk of the correspondence dealing with 1939 to 1977.
  - Undated, 1915-1938 (Box 1)
  - 1939-1943 (Box 1)
  - 1944-1958 (Box 1)
  - 1959-1962 (Box 1)
  - 1963-1965 (Box 1)
  - 1966-1968 (Box 1)
  - 1969-1970 (Box 1)
  - 1971 (Box 1)
  - 1972 (Box 1)
  - 1973 (Box 1)
  - 1974-June 1975 (Box 1)
  - July 1975-1977 (Box 1)
- Topical files 1928-1972
  The Topical Files series is arranged alphabetically by subject and contains materials on Kahn's professional work, associations, conferences, experiments and reports. This series also includes information on Kahn's career in the U.S. Army and his work on the Michigan State Health Department, where he developed the Kahn precipitation test for syphilis.
  - American Cancer Society Studies 1967-1968 (Box 1)
  - Appointments
    - (Howard University) (Box 1)
    - (University of Michigan) (Box 1)
  - Articles
    - Undated, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1939 re. blood tests (Box 1)
    - 1956-1970 (Box 1)
  - Atomic Energy Commission Study (charts and tabler) (Box 1)
  - Burroughs, John (Box 1)
  - Chicago Board of Health. Consultant (Box 1)
  - Children's Education. Correspondence 1967-1970 (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Conferences and trips
    - Brazil 1951 (Box 2)
    - Caribbean 1944 (Box 2)
    - Chile 1960 (Box 2)
    - Copenhagen. League of Nations Health Committee Serological Conference 1928 (Box 2)
    - Iran 1966 (Box 2)
    - Montevideo. League of Nations Health Committee Serological Conference 1930 (Box 2)
    - Philippines 1964 (Box 2)
    - Rome 1933 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Cosmos Club (support of applicants for admission) (Box 2)
  - Douglas Gardens Jewish Home for the Aged (Box 2)
  - Experiments (General)
    - Summary of John Eisses' experiments (Box 2)
    - Work on experiments, 175-179 (Box 2)
    - Toxin Lesion in Primary Immune Rabbits Experiments, 285-289 (Box 2)
    - Arthus Reaction (Box 2)
    - Flare-Up Reaction (Box 2)
    - Intracutaneous Toxin Injections (Box 2)
    - India Ink and Methylene Blue (Box 2)
    - Differential Effect of Toxin in X-Irradiated Rabbits (Box 2)
    - Localization in Various Tissues (Box 2)
    - Cobalt-60 Irradiated Plasma (Box 2)
    - Leucopenia (Box 2)
    - Comparison of Diphtheria (Box 2)
    - Horse Serum and Antitoxin Localization (Box 2)
    - Ephedrine and Histamine (Box 2)
    - Control Experiments (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Finances, personal (Box 2)
  - Howard University Health Research and Development Program (Box 2)
  - Irradiation. Some Effects of X-Irradiation on the Localizing Capacities of Different Areas of Tissue in Rabbits. Description of Experiments September 1961-June 1962 (Box 2)
  - Irradiation and Tissue Localizing Response.
    - Howard University Project 1969-1970 (Box 2)
    - Howard University Project 1971-1972 (Box 2)
  - Irradiation and Tissue Localizing Response.
    - Howard University Project. Grant,1971 (Box 2)
  - Irradiation Project. Howard University.
    - Site visits 1969 (Box 2)
    - Site visit 1971 (Box 2)
  - Irradiation and Tissue Immunity. Tables and Charts (Box 2)
  - Irradiation. Charts (Box 2)
  - Irradiation. Tables (Box 2)
  - Kahn, David. Correspondence 1944-1945 (Box 2)
  - Kahn, Dina (Box 2)
  - Letters from the children (Box 2)
  - Letters of congratulation on receiving the American Association for the Advancement of Science Award (Box 2)
  - Letters of Congratulation on the 25th Anniversary of the Kahn Reaction (Box 2)
  - "Localizing Response to Antigen in Immunity and Irradiation Effect." Manuscript (Box 2)
  - McDermott,Elizabeth. Correspondence 1928-1973 (Box 2)
  - Michigan State Health Department Laboratory (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous papers and scientific notes (Box 3)
  - Nominations for awards (Box 3)
  - Pfeiffer Foundation 1971 (Box 3)
  - Research Funds (Box 3)
  - Research Projects (Box 3)
  - Research Reports (Box 3)
  - Reuben L. Kahn Laboratory in Immunology. Hadassah Medical School, Hebrew University (Box 3)
  - Reviews
    - An Introduction to Universal Serological Reaction in Health and Disease (Box 3)
    - Serology in Syphilis Control (Box 3)
    - Serology with Lipid Antigen (Box 3)
    - Tissue Immunity (Box 3)
  - School papers. Valparaiso University 1907-1910 (Box 3)
  - Serologic Consultation Service (Box 3)
  - Speeches, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - "Studies on Metastasis II: In Relation to Intensity of Tumor Irradiation." Manuscript (Box 3)
  - Syphilis. Unpublished manuscripts (Box 3)
  - Testimonials and tributes (Box 3)
  - Tissue Immunity
    - 1936-1937 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence 1936 (Box 3)
    - Charts and Graphs 1956 (Box 3)
  - Tissue Immunity and Irradiation. Experiments 1962-1963 (Box 3)
  - Tissue Localization
    - Injected Antitoxins (Box 3)
    - Role in Hypersensitivity of Infection (Box 3)
    - Charts (Box 3)
  - U.S. Army (Box 3)
  - U.S. Navy (Box 3)
  - Universal Serologic Reaction Following Irradiation. Final Report to the Division of Biology and Medicine of the Atomic Energy Commission (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, 2 folders
    - Diary September-November 1924, May 1925 (Box 3)
    - Account of trip to Italy 1933 (Box 3)
    - Autographs (Box 3)
    - Collection of quotes (Box 3)
- Publications 1916-1967
  The Publications series includes a list of Kahn's publications and copies of many of his published articles and books.
  - List of Publications, 1 folders (Box 4)
  - Published articles
    - Reprints
      - Undated, 1923-1959 (Box 4)
      - 1960-1972 (Box 4)
    - References on the Kahn Reaction 1922-1931, 4 volumes (Box 4)
    - Collected Studies 1916-1959, 3 volumes (Box 4)
  - Books
    - Serum Diagnosis of Syphilis Precipitation, 1925 (Box 5)
    - The Kahn Test: A Practical Guide, 1928 (Box 5)
    - The Kahn Test: A Practical Guide, 1931 (Russian Translation) (Box 5)
    - La Reaccion Kahn, 1938 (Box 5)
    - Tissue Immunity, 1936 (Box 5)
    - Serology in Syphilis Control, 1942 (Box 5)
    - Serology with Lipid Antigen, 1950 (Box 5)
    - Universal Serological Reaction, 1951 (Box 5)
  - AEC Annual Progress Reports 1957-1967, 1 volumes (Box 5)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series contains photographs of Kahn's professional achievements and his personal family. Included are photographs of award ceremonies honoring Kahn's work, images of Kahn's laboratories and experiments and a personal family photograph album.
  - Awards to Reuben Leon Kahn (RLK) (Box 5)
  - Burroughs, John (Box 5)
  - Colleagues and students (Box 5)
  - Conference, Santiago, Chile 1960 (Box 5)
  - Family and friends (Box 5)
  - Honorary degree, Medical School of the National University, Athens, Greece (Box 5)
  - Kahn, Dina (Mrs. RLK), with RLK and alone (Box 5)
  - Kahn, Reuben L
    - Formal portraits (Box 5)
    - In laboratory, office, and teaching (Box 5)
    - Informal (Box 5)
    - With colleagues and students (Box 5)
  - Kahn Laboratory dedication, Teheran, Iran 1966 (Box 5)
  - McDermott, Elizabeth (Box 5)
  - Reuben L. Kahn Award (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - Experiments
    - Flare-up Reactions. Experiment 163 (Box 5)
    - Flare-up Reactions. Experiments 212 February 1964 and 218, March 1964 (Box 5)
      (1st Taxoid experiment)
    - Flare-up Reactions. Experiment 222 (Box 5)
    - Flare-up Reactions. Flare-up dater (Box 5)
    - Irradiation (Box 5)
    - Irradiation and Tissue Immunity (Box 5)
    - Irradiation and Tissue Localization (Box 5)
    - Irradiation-Rabbits (Box 5)
    - Irradiation-Rabbits. Experiment 139 October 26, 1962 (Box 5)
    - Localization. Role in hypersensitivity of infection October 1967 (Box 5)
  - Photo Album, circa 1910-1920 (Box 5)
    (personal photos)